<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A true discourse of the discomfiture of the Duke of Aumalle, vvith his troupes of horsmen in Picardie, by the Duke of Longueville Also other troupes of men discomfited in Beausse, by the Lord of Chastillon: together with the king of Nauarre his letters to the inhabitants of Orleans.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 32KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A01178</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853047</idno>
  <idno type="VID">18410</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248555327</idno>
  <idno type="STC">STC 11291</idno>
  <idno type="STC">ESTC S117837</idno>
  
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99853047e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A01178)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 18410)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1545:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A true discourse of the discomfiture of the Duke of Aumalle, vvith his troupes of horsmen in Picardie, by the Duke of Longueville Also other troupes of men discomfited in Beausse, by the Lord of Chastillon: together with the king of Nauarre his letters to the inhabitants of Orleans.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 5-21, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Richard Field, according to the French copies first printed at Tours,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1589.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Peterborough Cathedral. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Aumale, Charles de Lorraine, --  duc d', 1554-1631.</term>
               <term type="personal_name">Longueville, Henri I d'Orléans, --  duc de, 1568-1595.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">France --  History --  Wars of the Huguenots, 1562-1598 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:18410:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18410:1"/>
            <p>A TRVE DISCOVRSE OF THE DISCOMFITVRE OF THE DVKE OF AVMALLE, VVITH HIS TROVPES OF HORSMEN IN PICAR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DIE, BY THE DVKE OF LONGVE-VILLE.</p>
            <p>Also other troupes of men discomfited in Beausse, by the Lord of Chastillon:</p>
            <p>Together with the king of Nauarre his letters to the Inhabitants of Orleans.</p>
            <p>AT LONDON Printed by Richard Field, according to the French Copies first printed at Tours. 1589.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:18410:2"/>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:18410:2"/>
            <head>A DISCOVRSE VPON THE DISCOMFITVRE OR OVERTHROW THAT THE DVKE OF Aumalle, and Lord of Ballagnay with their troupes of men sustayned by the Duke of Longue-ville, and other Lords and Chiefetaines on the king his part. And of the raysing of the siege at the towne of Senlis in Picardie.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is well knowen in Fraunce, how at the end of April last, Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sieur de Thore, in the kings be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe, went vp and downe in the towne of Senlis, conferring with the good and faithfull inhabitants thereof, and séeking to maintaine the people in their due obedience to the king his Maiestie. He then had thrée dayes space before that the Parisians (who were amased to see the so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine reducing of the said towne to his Maiesties obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence) could come thither, or could cause the Duke of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>malle to come and besiege the foresaid Senlis: during which time of thrée dayes the said Monsieur de Thore had leysure both to furnish the town with victual &amp; munition, which he did aboundantly prouide of all things necessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie for the kéeping and defence thereof. Also he caused to come thither, of choise men, out of euery the villages in the valley and Duchie of Montmorency, a sufficient companie to fortefie the towne: so that there were two thousand able and resolute fighting men, at the least, who
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:18410:3"/>were ready to stand against any forces that should séeke to assault the towne. This he did, not that the place was of such strength, (for that was weake inough) but repo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing trust in the courage and faithfull mindes of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants and souldiers that were there. Then the Lord of Mainneuille, who is now called the Gouernor of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris because the Duke of Maienne was not there, came first out with a companie of Parisians well armed, and the Duke of Aumalle was there almost as soone as he, with a companie of braue horsemen, and a forte of soote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men: and they besieged the towne, being at the first dash to the number of foure thousand men. Immediatly, the Parisians and other their partakers, came posting from many places, being well horsed &amp; furnished, so as in short space there were gathered fiue or sixe thousand men well prouided besieging the towne. On Friday the fift of May they sent to Paris, for to haue ordinance, and the same day were thrée péeces sent them and no moe: that is, two Canons and one Culuerine, which, for that none could be found to conduct them with so much spéede as they wished, the way that they vsed was thus: There hauing béene an order taken at Paris not long before, that of sixtéeue Colonelles that were in sixtéen quarters or parts of the Citie, one should march euery day in good order, and wel furnished, with eleuen or twelue hundred men, out of the City, for to kéepe the Castle of Saint Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, whatsoeuer might happen: this Friday it happened that the Colonel and Captaine of Aubret his regiment was assembled for to go and gather together another re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giment and companie Colonelle for captaine Compans, the one of the Shirifes of the said Citie of Paris: the said regiment of the captaine and Colonel d'Aubret was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strayned, going along vpon our Ladies bridge, whereas they should haue turned by the Greue, toward S. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thonies gate, for to goe to the Castle of S. Vincent (whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a litle before were gone their baggage, their apparel,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:18410:3"/>victuall and such like) that they might goe foorth straight by S. Martines gate, to conduct the said ordinance, which was carried a little before toward the Suburbs, vnder the charge of one Brigard, the procurator of the hostell of the citie: and the next day, being Saterday, in the eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, they came before Senlis: where at the first cōming, they hayled the town with a canon shot, at y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> noyse wherof on a sodain all the souldiers came to the wall of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> towne, and offred to make as great a breach in the wall, as they would demaund without their vsing of canon shot, séeing that they promised to geue the assault: and hereupon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing presently summoned to yéeld vnto a composition, they promised to make answere on the morow: wherupō a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port came to Paris, that they of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> town had offred <hi>3.</hi> score thousād crownes as some said; <hi>100.</hi> thousand crownes as other said: for their answere they hāged out &amp; spread vpon the walles outward a great paynted cloth, in which they had hanged pourtrayed together two persons, the Duke of Mayenne on the one side, &amp; the Duke of Aumalle on y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> other, and the Lady Montpensier knéeling at the feete of them with her head all vncouered, wéeping, and tearing her haire: and the people cried out with vile opprobrious spéeches, that the same was the portraiture of the compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition that they demaunded. This draue them to send a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine vnto Paris for strength of Canon shot to beate the towne to dust, as they said. The messengers were tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned away thence as sleightly as might be, without obtei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning that they came for, and excuse was made that they lacked bullets, and such péeces as they demaunded: and that was partly also for a distrust they had in the Duke of Aumalle, who had oftentimes refused to come and ioine himselfe with the Duke of Mayenne, by reason of ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that is betwixt them: moreouer, because that they thought that the Lord of Ballagny was comming thither with great strength of men, and seuen Canons. Before the comming of which Lord of Ballagny, they of Senlis
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:18410:4"/>made a sallie out of the towne of a hundred horsemen: whereat they that besieged the towne were so amazed, that they thought best to fly, and especially the Parisians cast away their armes, flying, and hiding themselues in bushes on euery side: of which hundred horsemen, fiftie came backe into the towne, and the other fiftie kept the field for to ayde any that might come to succour them. Then the Lord of Ballagny with his companies of men, came and ioyned with the Duke of Aumalle, &amp; they with their tenne Canons, began the battery on Wednesday, the seuentéenth of May, and within a while the souldiers confusedly gaue assault to the foresaid towne by the breach made the same day, which was in trueth a great breach: notwithstanding, they had the repulse, by reason they did that without the appointment of the Generall of the armie. About noone word came that the Duke of Longueuille accompanied with the Lord of Humieres, the Lord Bonniuet, the Lord dela Noue, the Lord of Giury, of Mesuiller, of Tour, and other Nobles of the Prouince of Picardie, were at hand, to the number of a thousand horsemen, and thrée thousand sootemen, for to ayde the towne of Senlis. Wherupon, the foresaid Lord of Ballagny pitched in campe the best power of his men: &amp; being then accompanied with the Lords of Main-uille, of Sayssenall, of Mesieres, of Congy and others, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming neare the said Duke of Longueuille, the horsemen of Cambray marched on in good order, thinking to ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the footemen of the said Duke of Longueille: which footemen deuided in the middle, and gaue roome for the ordinance, which shot so furiously among them of Cābray and among the Wallons, that séeing so many of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues ouerthrowen, they were forced to retire. After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, they comming to a set battaile, fought stoutly on both sides, and with great courage, the ordinance of the said Duke of Longueuille, still making great spoyle a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the souldiers of the Duke of Aumalle, in so much
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:18410:4"/>that the foūldiers began to conceiue such great-dread, as neither the Duke of Anmalle, nor the Lord of Ballagny could euer gather them together againe by their chearful words, or goodly shewes whatsoeuer: and the armie that held the siege fled all away presently. Which thing en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged the Duke of Longueuille, with those that had béene besieged, issuing thick out then, to follow them in chase, and kill them with handy blowes. By which meane they hold now safely the towne Senlis, haue gotten all the munition that the Duke of Aumalle had, powder, bullets, and ordinance, about fiftéene hundred, or néere two thousand be slaine in that place, hesides those that were pursued and slaine as they fled in diuers villages. The said Duke of Aumalle is hurt, and the Lord of Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lagny is also hurt in the face, though it be but a little: and the Duke of Aumalle is gone back to S. Denis, fearing lest he should not be in safetie, nor very well welcome to Paris: the Lord of Ballagny saued himselfe by flying to Paris, there fayning that he would take order for the ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering together again of the souldiers, because he would seeme to threaten his enemies, and to encourage again the braue souldiers of Paris.</p>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>The Copie of a letter, written by a certaine Lord, to a kinsman of his, the twentieth of May. 1589.</head>
               <p>COusin, I stayed this bearer vntill I had some good newes to write. I euen now haue receiued some by a man that I sent to Paris: he saw the companies of monsieur d'Aumalle, that were discomfited at Senlis by monsieur de Longueuille, accompanied with monsieur de la Noue: he gat safe himselfe the third day after his flight to Saint Denis. Ballagny is safe at Paris, and cheareth vp the people that be altogether amazed and adread at this ouerthrow. He promiseth them new forces out of the low Countreyes, but he hath the money. Iudge you
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:18410:5"/>whether this be the way to make them wel againe. They haue lost tenne great péeces of ordinance, thrée that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longed to the Arcenall, sixe to Peronne, and one to Ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens: that was done on Wednesday toward euening. My man could not tell me what men they lost, for he came in haste to bring mee this good tidings. Make acquainted herewith Master Warden of Seux, and M. Warden of Souuray. You know also what monsieur de Chastillon did on Thursday toward euening. This hath béene an vnluckie wéeke for them, and so I trust will the whole yeare be. Continue your frendship to me, and make account, good cousin, that I will doe the like to you alwaies.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your well affectioned Cousin, and better friend, M. R.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:18410:5"/>
            <head>THE LETTER OF A CER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TAINE GENTLEMAN OF BEAVSSE to a friend of his being a Citizen of Paris, touching the ouerthrow of the forces of Monsieur d'Aumalle, written on Thursday the 18. of May. 1589.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Haue béene euen amazed a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand times, to thinke of the newes that haue bene reported to me for certaine &amp; true, touching the esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blishing of your matters at Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris, and that you haue so often sent me for true, many tidings that were but inuented by some cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning fellowes, who deceiue &amp; abuse you, while they goe about other manner purposes than they make you acquainted with: which is the cause, Sir, and my good frend, that I haue written this vnto you, that ye may not be ignorant of that which happened ye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterday: knowing that you shall haue the matter repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted there with you farre otherwise than is true, because they would not haue the Citizens discouraged, and to féed you dayly with hope of some high enterprises, that you expect at the hands of this holy and inuincible army, that Monsieur the Duke of Mayenne hath so long kept in this Countrey without doing any thing, making great pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mises, the least of which is, that he will bring the kings Maiestie to that passe that the most mutinous fellowes in your Citie desire to haue him: and for a triall, he hath in déede, when the greatest forces of the king were away, drawen nigh enough. True it is that he wet back again,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:18410:6"/>as was best for him to doe, and after that he had done somewhat as he might, being obstinate a long time, after his so great enterprising he gaue place to the kings pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence, and at the comming of the king of Nauarre, he gat him barke as soone as he vnderstoode that he was neare, but this is not y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> onely argumēt that I write of, but for to tell you that we knew how discontented the strangers and Wallons of his armie were, so as they would needes haue béene gone, and that the said Lord had much a doe to make them stay, and I beleue the cause why they be not yet come backe, is the hope that he put them in of recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing new forces, and fresh supplie from the companies in Picardie, which he looked for frō the Lord of Aumalle, I tell you plaine that this their hope is choaked: for on Thursday last at thrée of the clock after noone, as I vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstoode by a frend of mine, the Lord of Chastillon, pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing by Boisgency, and being sent to the warre by the K. of Nauarre, with two hundred horsemen, and as many harquebusiers, vnderstanding that certaine of the Duke of Aumalle his troupes came that way, for to set vpon the Lord of Lorges, who had beaten the way the day be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, directed his course toward Bonneuall, and with him twenty of his Gentlemen for scoutes, who were led by the Lord of Founquerolles: they méet with Arclein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ville, gouernor for the Duke of Mayenne at Chartres, who had with him fiftie horses, they make towards hun for to bid him battaile, he méeteth with them, they vse the matter so that they kill fiue or sixe of his men: he retireth and geueth Alarme to the troupe that was but a quarter of a mile thence, the troupe came orderly vnder the lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the Lord of Saueuze, where were the Lords of Brosses, that had a faire troupe of sixe or seuen score gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen, all the choise of noble birth in Picardie on their side, to the number of thrée hundred horse, with fiue and twenty or thirtie harquebusiers, with the Lord of Force<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ville, &amp; many other Gentlemen of name: then the Lord
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:18410:6"/>of Chastilion changed his pace to a trotte, for to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine them. Charboniere and Harambure with their cō, panies of light horsemen, were on his left wing on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther side. Saueuze setting forth before his harquebusiers, set his company of Lanciers in rankes, and commeth a great pace, without breaking ranke, for the space of a quarter of a mile. The trumpets sound the charge on both sides, the Lord of Chastillon casteth about a little, to stay for his harquebusiers, and placing them, he maketh two hostes of the horsemen that he hath, he goeth to the skirmish. Saueuze commeth foorth very brauely &amp; coura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giously, galloping for thirty paces, his harquebusiers on horseback geue the onset néere inough: the L of Chastillō his footemen receiueth them: who, after the first harque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>busiers were discharged, euen during the fight, rushed in among the horsemen, killed many horses with their swordes, and of them were slain one that had béene of the king of Nauarres garde, and two souldiers of the garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of Boisgeney, and no mo. Saueuze, who on a sodaine had bent himselfe against the light horsemen, taketh right, and chargeth so furiously the Lord of Chastillon, that the first rankes were broken, he vnhorsed and layde along, and eight or tenne of his Gentlemen incurred the like miffortune: among whom were Mouy, Rosny, S. Sere, Fresillon and Chamballam: two or three of which were hurt with launces, and twenty or thirty of their horses slaine. The Brosses at the same time set vpon the rereward of the Lord of Chastillon, so that his troupe was greatly troubled. At length the Lord of Chastillon, and others that were ouerthrowen, recouered thēselues, and fell a fighting with their swords on foote, and he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe aduentured so farre, that he was hurt on the face with a broken launce. In the meane while Harambure, who had the leading of the king of Nauarre his light horsemen, next to whom was Fouquerolles in ranke, set vpon Saueuze and his companie so furiously, that he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:18410:7"/>and brake ray, so as he made them flie, and disperse themselues in such fort, that they could not be gathered together againe. They were then pursued, and stayed in the same place where were assembled of Picalds aboue sixe score Gentlemen: the residue were pursued a good mile and a halfe, and were slaine by the way flying, to the number of threescore &amp; mo, with al the harquebusiers, two Cornets taken, and the bearers of them slaine, forty Gentlemen taken, among which were Saueuse and Forceuille: Many of account were hurt, where as the Lord of Chastilion lost but one Gentleman, and but thrée souldiers as I said before, and there were hurt none but Chamballam and two or thrée others that were hurt with launces and swords, yet their hurts are not deadly. The Lord of Chastillon woon the field. This is a begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to make them looke vnto their owne consciences, that are risen vp against the king. I was desirous to let you vnderstand hereof, that ye might know the trueth, which is hidden from you by coosening shifts that they haue to féede you with false rumors. I learned this by a Gentleman that brought a letter, the copie of which I now send you. He vnderstood all the particulars by them that were at the discomfiture. Looke to your selfe, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uise such as are well disposed to take a good heart to thē. I will now trouble you no longer, vntill I haue other good newes come to my hand: in the meane while I commend me to your good grace, praying God to kéepe you. From Chasteaudun, May <hi>19. 1589</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:18410:7"/>
               <head>The Copie of a letter written by a Lord, to a kinsman of his, vpon the discomfiture of the troupes of the L. of Aumalle, neare Bonneuall, on Thursday the 18. of May 1589.</head>
               <p>COusin, you shall vnderstand by N. the happy execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that Monsieur de Chastillon made yesterday at foure of the clock neare Bonneuall, vpon the troupes of Monsieur d'Aumalle, being led by Sauenze. He took Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueuze and another of the chiefetaines: some of the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines were slaine, and about two humdred of their men, the residue are prisoners, and their colours are gotten a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way. To be short, this is as happy a victorie as any that hath béene gotten in these warres. All the kings enemies that came out of Picardie are stayed there. This will be good newes for the king, and fitte for his dealing with them of Poictiers. The foresaid N. will tell you all par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly. Resting my selfe thereupon, I will say no more, but will pray God, good Cousin, to kéep you.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your very good and faithfull friend. M. N.</signed>
                  <dateline>From Saint Die <date>May <hi>19.</hi>
                     </date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:18410:8"/>
            <head>A LETTER OF THE KING OF NAVARRE TO THE MAISTERS of Orleans, written the two and twentieth of May, 1589. From Baugency.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Riendes, I am very sory to come and visit you with such a company and to be constrained after so long time that I haue beene comming toward you, to shew vnto this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince and to your neighbours a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout, those verations and discom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities that warre brings with it. I haue notwithstanding heretofore yéelded testimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies enough both before God and men, of the distiking that I had in maintaining warres: I haue by many and sundry actions shewed, that my bearing armes was to none other end, but to procure peace, that in hope hereof I am bold to beare armes: hauing this conscience, I trust that God will blesse me in my battailes: especially now, when as euen in the sight of all Christendome my King hath honoured me so much as to yéeld him selfe the iudge of my right intentions, and he is become the best witnes that I could wish, of mine innecency. I haue in generall many times exhorted Fraunce to desire the owne quiet and rest. I haue according to my duety in seruice to the King my Lord and maister, and for the good of my ceun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey foreseene and manifestly spoken, euer since the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the last ciuill warres, against the euils wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they haue now filled the estate of this realme. My foreseeings thereof proued as true as my protestations and speakings of it were vnprofitable, to my great grief
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:18410:8"/>(God hauing sent his rod of dissention vpon this poore Realme.) Yet will I not cease to deserue well of the Realme: my Countrey shall rather faile in duetie to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards me a Citizen thereof, than I a Citizen will faile in duetie toward my Countrey: and as long as I shall sée this sicke commonweale breath or gaspe, I will not once leaue it, vntill it be either wholy cured, or that I be dead with it. Looke what I haue done in generall, that will I doe in particulars, wheresoeuer occasion shall be offered. And I am glad that comming to you (before that y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> matter come to be tried by force of armes) I may assay what good order, reason and milde courtesie may winne your hearts vnto: For you, whatsoeuer madnes, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectious disease God hath layd vpon you, those are but things now ordinarily incident to Fraunce: I assure my selfe that you are of the race of those men that alone did assist king Charles the seuenth when he fled to Bourges, and ayded him against England, against Burgonie, Guienne, Normandie, Britaine, and almost all France that was confederate against hun. I cannot but stil won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and am astonied to thinke how ye should become so sencelesse, as now to make no more account of that most famous title of your Auncestors: I cannot deuise what argument might be so effectuall, and of such importance, as to make you so lightly to leaue your side lity &amp; loyalty, the oath which euen from his birth euery one of you hath sworne to his Countrey, the vow that ye haue reiterated or made againe and againe, at the coronation of so many kings, and the same oath, wherwith you haue stand boūd these many yeares, and yet so abide vnder this king, whom God at this present hath geuen vs. I cannot ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine what might driue you to thinke that a slauish estate vnder the Spaniards, should be more pleasant than to liue at libertie, according to the manner of France: that the crosse of Lorraine, or of Burgondie, should better go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne the estate, than the auncient and fortunate Flour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deluces,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:18410:9"/>which be reuerenced all Christendome ouer. To conclude, that the name of a traytor, of a rebell against his magistrate, against his Prince, to be a despiser of his commandements, and a violater of his maiestie, should be better, and more honourable than the name of a good Citizen, and a faithfull subiect. But you will say, it is an vnféemely thing for me that haue borne armes for the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie of conscience, if I should blame your doings, that are grounded vpon a colour of the like. That which may serue for an excuse to those of the religion, ye would hold to be lawfull for you: but séeing you like to take them for example, goe yet no further than they. If they would haue gone about to plant their religion in Fraunce by dinte of sword: if they had gone about to make any warre offensiue to the king, before they were set vpon, &amp; forced to defend themselues, O what would men haue said then? They neuer did so: they alwaies stood vpon their defence, alwaies ready to receiue peace whensoeuer it was offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: and yet notwithstanding, onely because that the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed of the Lord, he to whom the scepter belongeth, was against thē, God did not alwaies blesse their armes: for to declare vnto the people that there is nothing so deare vnto God, as the maintaining of the Maiestie of kings, which is an image of his owne maiestie, and they are his Lieutenants on earth. You haue heretofore accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed those of Rochell, you haue vniustly called them tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors and rebels, because they would not geue ouer the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie of their conscience, nor hazard their liues to the mercie of their enemies. If you spight at them with those goodly names, stay a while as well as they, vntill you sée Edicts published, by which all the Catholikes of France shalbe accounted and vsed as traytors: waite till ye see them slaine throughout all the good cities and townes that be neare you, and that an armie of men shall come thundering vpon your walles for to spoyle you: then shal feare indéede excuse your taking armes, and necessitie
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:18410:9"/>your rebellion. But vntill that time, my friends, what hast haue ye to make your childrē a race of faithlesse truce breakers, rebels and traytors. But ye will say that then it will be no time, and that you will prouide for that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hand. If ye would estéeme your cause and end to be better than theirs of the religion, ye must think that it wil necessarily follow, that God wil no lesse fauour you than them, séeing you follow them for example. Call to minde, that they had to deale with the state of Fraunce when it was flourishing, with kings that were well obeyed, well setled, that they were often surprised, and their chiefe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines slaine. They neuer gaue a blow, but first they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued twaine: they neuer had the forecasts that you haue, and for all that they be yet aliue and at libertie, God be praysed: will he doe lesse for you when ye shal be set vpon? And ye all know that you are yet stronger than they, and that you can neuer haue the enemies that they haue had. Who doeth make you to runne headlong so rashly? what madnes is it, for feare of some euil that may displease you hereafter, to make your selues presently vnfortunate, and in miserable state? for to hinder a fault that may be, to committee a manifest crime: for preuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting an euill farre of, to cause and suffer an innumerable sort of euils: for assurance of libertie to your children, to bring them vp in bondage: for making sure to them their quiet estate &amp; their goods, to geue them ouer vnto warres and robberie? Beléeue mee, my friends, they that put this in your heads, doe goe about to make your backs as footsteps to get vp vnto the scaffold of their ambition: but they forgat to tel you, that if the scaffold fall (as no doubt it shall) they shal come downe headlong, and you will be stifled vnder them, if they come not downe betimes, and that you doe not get you away before all be ouerthrowē, Aduise you wel of the matter, it is but to put you in a vaine feare, to perswade you that our king (who is the most Catholike king that euer was) will compell you to
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:18410:10"/>leaue your Catholike religion, he is farre from threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning you that. But what, should I be he that should doe it? I am not your king, neither shall I euer be (if it please God.) If I should be called thereto, I would not be so vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise, but I would flie all occasions that might breede ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill warre and dissention in a Realme. I am glad that I may now talke so familiarly and neighborly with you. You haue séene there but for two dayes, wednesday and thursday last, the beginnings of the successe that God sent your armed men at Senlis, and here, euen in the view of two of the greatest cities of Fraunce: Looke vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it at is not for you to make warre against your king, whether he had occasion to punish the Duke of Guise, yea or no. There haue at other times béene in Fraunce some of as great a house as he, that haue béene more shamefully vsed: and yet the people sooke not an euill quarrell in hand. Soueraigns are not to render an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt of their scepter to any but to God: when things are done, we must looke to obey them: you shall neuer doe wel as long as your foundation is so ill. And if ye would complaine, that gouernors would be set ouer you, or a garrison of men that would treade you vnder foote, and make you for<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s and such like: albeit these be the ordinary complaints of all cities and townes, which be not lawfull in a peaceable and well gouerned Realme, yet the disor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of our Realme hath made them fitter to be receiued. If you would but desire it, I know not certainly my L. the king his mind, but I am surely perswaded, that for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getting your offences, he will be at one with you, if ye will but frame your selues to acknowledge your faults, and craue parden. And doing thus, you shal not néed feare that any but your owne selues shall driue you to leaue your religion, that any other shall builde your forts but your selues, that ye shalbe your owne garrison. And that is more fitte and profitable for you, than to be alwaies in paine and at alarme, hauing néede alwaies of an armie
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:18410:10"/>to garde you whensoeuer ye goe out at the gates neuer so little, to sée your corne fields, your houses and vines on a fire, your wiues and childrē spoiled, while you go about to reuenge another mans quarrell. My friends, if I were a Spaniard, or one of Lorraine, I would not talke thus vnto you, I would be glad to sée you at war among your selues, and to sée my selfe euen at your gates ready to spoile you, or to besiege you: I would imagine that I had the spoile of you already. This is it whereat the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies doe glory and boast, &amp; if I were as they be, I would wish it no otherwise: but I am a Frenchman, I am one of your Princes, I haue a right in looking to the safegard of you, therefore speake I this vnto you. You may, if yeé will, kéepe you where ye are in safetie and rest, being masters of your owne houses, so as ye will gently yeelde obedience and dueties, as you owe, vnto your king: and as your example hath made many fooles, deale so now, as by following of you many may become wise. And beléeue me friends this one word, that in trueth if but your only citie had rebelled, ye ought to haue beene sore punished, but seeing the contagion is generall, it must be cured by clemencie. Certaine it is, neuerthelesse, that as the citie or towne that first began rebellion shall by inst desert be the more punished for crample sake, so that which first shall seeke for mercie, shall farre more easily finde fauor, than that citie or towne that shall stay vnto the last pinch. I assure you my friends, that I shalbe glad, and think my selfe happy, if I may be employed to winne you by cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mencie, rather than to subdue you by force: For I am a Frenchman, and yours.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>HENRIE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>